<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true church of Christ exposed to the view of all sober Christians, from the Word of God, sound reason, and the ancient fathers / by James Salgado, a Spaniard, a converted priest.</title>
            <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42935</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875961</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2294:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true church of Christ exposed to the view of all sober Christians, from the Word of God, sound reason, and the ancient fathers / by James Salgado, a Spaniard, a converted priest.</title>
                  <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for the Author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 46-47 misprinted 47-46.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams' Library (London, England)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestant converts --  England.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE CHURCH OF CHRIST, EXPOSED To the View of all SOBER CHRISTIANS, from the Word of GOD, Sound Reaſon, AND THE Ancient FATHERS.</p>
            <p>By JAMES SALGADO, <hi>a Spaniard, a Converted Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for the Author 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152349:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152349:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>HENEAGE,</hi> Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis moſt Important Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, which concerns the Converſion of a Man to God, cannot better be offered to any Perſon, than to one that
<pb facs="tcp:152349:3"/>manages the greateſt Affairs of a Mighty Monarch; to the Glory of his God, to the Credit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Prince, to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Repute of the Nation, to the gladding of the hearts of all good Subjects therein, and the Terrour of Offenders; to his own Immortal praiſe here, and Immortal Felicity hereafter, with univerſal, ſteady, unſhaken Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Juſtice and Integrity; It is, to ſpeak in ſhort, moſt agreeable for one that is the Quinteſſence of all Excellencies, both Divine and Humane.</p>
            <p>The boldneſs which I have to preſent this Book to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb facs="tcp:152349:3"/>doth not only bid me hope for Excuſe, but alſo promiſe my ſelf that your Honour will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it according to your wont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Noble and Generous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention, being your Poor Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer tenders it with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt Reverence and Reſpects imaginable.</p>
            <p>I humbly pray your Lordſhip to take both my Self and Book to your Honours Protection; and it ſhall be my daily Prayers to Almighty God, to take under his Eſpecial Charge your Honours Perſon, and under his Eſpecial Conduct all your Honours Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo that both may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:152349:4"/>to his Divine Majeſty, and his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and to all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Spirits; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Servant, <hi>JAMES SALGADO.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152349:4"/>
            <head>THE TRUE CHURCH OF CHRIST, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT was not without Reaſon that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers compared the Church to the Ark of <hi>Noah;</hi> becauſe that as none that were out of the Ark could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape deſtruction by the Flood; ſo none that are without the Boſom of the Church can eſcape Everlaſting Damnation; for thoſe that are no Members of the Church, cannot partake of her peculiar Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, ſuch as Vocation, Juſtification, Sanctification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without which it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to attain Eternal Life: And as any Member cut off from the Body is thereby deprived of Life, Senſe and Motion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152349:5"/>it is no more united to, nor influenced from the Head; even ſo thoſe that are cut off from the Church, are thereby deprived of Eternal Life, becauſe they are not united unto Chriſt, who is the Head of the Church; and therefore want that influence of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is the Author of all Spiritual Life.</p>
            <p>For this reaſon <hi>David</hi> affirms, that the Heathen knew not the Laws of God, even becauſe they were not in the Communion of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to which the Church was confined under the Old Teſtament, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 147.19, 20. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> doth yet further confirm this Aſſertion; <hi>At that time you were without Chriſt, being Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens from the Commonwealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Strangers from the Covenant of Promiſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no hope, and without God in the world, Eph.</hi> 2.12. Namely, becauſe they were not in the Boſom of the Church, they were therefore excluded from the Communion of Chriſt, who is the faithful Husband of the Church his only Spouſe, as he himſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.1. <hi>My Dove, my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled, is but one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when the Fathers uſed this ſimilitude, they meant the Univerſal Church, whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deriveth from <hi>Abel,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152349:5"/>deduceth the continuation thereof even to the end of the World: Therefore it is not this or that Church, in this or that part of the World, that can be called Catholick in this ſenſe; but that Church which was, which is, and which is to come, and comprehends the Triumphant as well as the Militant. And if that be properly Catholick, which hath been always and every where believed by all <hi>(Vincent. Lirinenſis contra profanas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitates)</hi> then that is the Catholick Church which hath and will be always found in all Nations; for the thing ruled cannot be narrower than the Rule, and Faith cannot be found but in believers.</p>
            <p>I don't deny that there are many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Aſſemblies, and many Provincial or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Churches, and ſome of theſe purer than others; but none of theſe Aſſemblies or Churches can be called Catholick, taking the word ſtrictly, becauſe they are only parts or members conſtituting one general body; and therefore cannot be called univerſal without a plain contradiction, unleſs you would give to the Hand or Foot the name of the whole body.</p>
            <p>Hence it follows, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church being but a particular Church (ſuppoſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152349:6"/>that it were <hi>Orthodox,</hi> which yet we utterly deny) cannot claim unto it ſelf alone, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively to other Churches that profeſs Chriſt, the Title of Catholick.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I am not ſo rigid as to exclude the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and her Followers from the Latitude of the Univerſal Church; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe beſides that men living in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but in the ſimplicity of their heart profeſſing God and his Chriſt, and ſincerely endeavouring to work out their Salvation (although in many points they neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the thing it ſelf, nor the manner of the thing, becauſe of an invincible igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) may attain unto eternal life; <hi>for God is no reſpecter of perſons, but in every Nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted with him, Act.</hi> 10.34, 35. I ſay, beſides this, the Popiſh Church may be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Church in a Phyſical though not in a Moral ſenſe, even rs an Adulterous Wife doth not loſe the name of a Wife, although ſhe loſe the name of an honeſt Wife.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> will have their Church to conſiſt in the Pope, or Council, or both, I ſhall evince their Church ſo taken to be fallible, erroneous and falſe.</p>
            <p>And although the Church in this ſenſe be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152349:6"/>but repreſentative; yet ſeeing all the reſt do depend upon her as infallible, and have nothing left them but a blind obedience, taking the denomination of the whole from the principal part, I rightly affirm that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is falſe, uncatholick, yea, and no Church at all.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, not contented to pronounce all Churches without their Communion He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Schiſmaticks, and therefore without any hope of Salvation, have more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over aſſerted, that their own Church is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and void of all Errour. A great Aſſertion indeed, and which is not only falſe in it ſelf, but alſo is one great reaſon why other Churches diſſenting from her, cannot joyn into one Body, nor hold Communion with her: For, beſides that no particular Church (ſuch as the <hi>Roman</hi> is) can be called infallible, it neceſſitates them, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> to worſhip they know not what, and erect an Altar <hi>to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in vain to diſpute concerning the property or priviledge of any thing, while they that attribute theſe priviledges to it, have no certain knowledge of the thing it ſelf: Therefore in vain do they aſſert, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152349:7"/>their Church is infallible, while they cannot determine when, or where this Church is. Some of them, as the <hi>Sorboniſts,</hi> do place it in the Council; others, as the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> in the Pope alone, and finally, others in them both both joyntly. Now chuſe which of thoſe you pleaſe, you'l find your ſelf involv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to inextricable difficulties; and, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, under a neceſſity to ſacrifice to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God, which I ſhall ſhortly evince.</p>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe, that the Church and her Infallibility conſiſts in the Council alone, you ſhall preſently be contradicted by ſome men of that ſame Church. But to paſs this, Whence pray doth it appear that this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil is infallible? For firſt, it is impoſſible, that of things of one and the ſame nature, there can be made up another thing of a quite contrary nature: Therefore all the Members, of which this Council conſiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallible, how comes the Council it ſelf to be infallible? for if this Infallibility came but then to the Council, when they met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to conſtitute one Synodical Body; where pray' was it before? in what corner of the World did it lurk? from whence, and in what manner did this good Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity come down upon the Fathers of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152349:7"/>Council? or what ſhall become of it after the Council is diſſolved? Where ſhall it compoſe its Head to reſt, that hath been toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and wearied by ſo many janglings and Gramatications.</p>
            <p>Moreover, how ſhall you know that all the Members of the Council have been lawfully or at all baptized, ſeeing you cannot be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the intention of the Prieſt, or Old Woman that baptized them, upon which the Efficacy of the Sacrament depends; that they were Canonically ordained, and not <hi>per ſaltum?</hi> that they were not intruded by force or Simony? All which are required to the conſtitution of a Biſhop <hi>in ſuo formali.</hi> And unleſs you can perſwade your ſelf, that you believe all theſe with a Divine and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Faith, you cannot imbrace their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees for infallible.</p>
            <p>Again, if this Infallibility of the Church do conſiſt in the Council, there ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways extant ſuch a Council, to which diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing Parties might have recourſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a final determination of their Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies; that ſo all ſcruples being removed out of their minds, they might live in peace and concord among themſelves. But where is all this to be found? And if there were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152349:8"/>ſuch a Council always in being, which yet is impoſſible, how ſhould you know that this Council is not miſguided by partiality; that it is not as bad as that of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> and needs not to be corrected by a ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Council? (as many Councils have been, if we believe <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>)</p>
            <p>You'l ſay perhaps that Chriſt promiſed unto his Diſciples, and conſequently to the Church, that <hi>the Spirit of truth ſhall come, and guide them into all truth,</hi> Joh. 16.13. and <hi>that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it,</hi> Mat. 16.18.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, I deny not that Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his Diſcipies the Holy Ghoſt, but extraordinary things are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with ordinary; for they received both the matter and words of what they wrote from the immediate inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt; but in after-Ages the Church was tyed to the Scriptures, as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for all manner of holy inſtruction, <hi>Cal.</hi> 1.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. which if the Fathers of the council do follow, it is not to be doubted but God will afford them the aſſiſtance of his Spirit: But it cannot be ſaid, that the Council doth hereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come infallible.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152349:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. When Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt the Church,</hi> he doth not underſtand any particular Churches of their Biſhops, but the Univerſal Church, which that it cannot erre in Fundamentals, we believe and aſſert.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How do you know that the Holy Spirit preſides in this or that Council, ſeeing the Council of <hi>Ariminum</hi> may be called a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil as well as the <hi>Nicene?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How can you be ſure of any Council, that the Members thereof ſpeak from a love to truth, and deſire of peace, or from the Dictates of the Holy Ghoſt, and not rather from partiality? that their Decrees are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more by the weight of Reaſon and Scriptures, than by the multitude of Votes; that it is not ſuch as the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> to which (as a Member of that Synod ſaid) the Holy Ghoſt was brought from <hi>Rome</hi> in the Bags of the <hi>Roman</hi> Pacquet, and ſtayed longer away when the waters did riſe, but came quickly thither when they were ſallen, as being afraid to be wet or drowned.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It's ridiculous for a Papiſt to go about to prove the Infallibility of Councils from Scripture; for I ask him this queſtion, Whence doth it appear that that Church is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152349:9"/>Infallible, whoſe office it is both to make a Rule or Canon, and to give Authority to the Scriptures? for they hold, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scriptures, as to us left, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Church: Now if the Church give the Scriptures their Authority, as to us, how can they convince us of the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee into what difficulties they involve themſelves, who place the Church with its Infallibility in the Council.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs, but rather more abſurd, to ſettle it in the Pope alone; an Aſſertion ſo fooliſh and ridiculous, that the very reciting of it might be a ſufficient confutation; namely, to place the Church in one Man; the Church, I ſay, which (even though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative) is formally a Congregation of many: Nevertheleſs we ſhall proceed in the Method we have begun.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuits do generally hold this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and affirm, that the Pope alone, like the <hi>Pythia</hi> of <hi>Delphos,</hi> may frame Decrees, and impoſe them upon the people.</p>
            <p>But the forementioned difficulties return; For how can you perſwade your ſelf that the Pope was Popable? that he was rightly, if at all baptized? that he obtained not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152349:9"/>the Popedom by force, by fraud, or by Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony? that he was a Man, and not a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? (for we have an inſtance of a Woman Pope, namely, Pope <hi>Jone</hi>) any of which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppoſed, renders the Pope no more a Pope.</p>
            <p>Moreover, How ſhall you know that the Pope when he went about the framing of his Decrees, neglected not the uſual prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, namely, Faſting and Prayer for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he acts by the advice of his Conclave, and not rather from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of his own private judgment or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. Now if theſe Conditions be wanting, the Decrees are not pronounced from the Chair, and therefore not infallible, nor obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Further, By what Argument can you be convinced, that this Infallibility doth not belong to the Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> (for example) as much as to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that it cannot be removed from the <hi>Roman Chair;</hi> for <hi>Gerſon</hi> hath written a Treatiſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poſſibility of removing it.</p>
            <p>Finally, It cannot be conceived that one ſingle man is Infallible in matters of Faith, ſeeing he hath no promiſe of an Infallible Spirit; and there are manifeſt examples of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152349:10"/>his having been actually deceived. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you will ſly to that Vulgar diſtinction of the Popes pronouncing from, or without his Chair; ſo that what he Decrees in the former way is infallible, though in the latter he may deceive, and be deceived.</p>
            <p>But you'l find that even this diſtinction can very little advantage, but rather preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice your Cauſe: For how can it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that one and the ſame Man, without any fear or compulſion, can contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in one and the ſame matter? Again, the Pope, who being out of the Chair may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, ought to adviſe with himſelf, as ſitting in the Chair, leſt he fall into an errour; or the Cardinals, if they would have this Holy Father to be always infallible, ſhould bind the good Old Man to the Chair with Chains, (as <hi>Prometheus</hi> was tyed to <hi>Caucaſus</hi>) that he may never be moved out of this Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seat. Beſides, it is manifeſt, that the Popes, even pronouncing from the Chair, have frequently erred; as appears by the examples of <hi>John</hi> the XXIII. <hi>Stephanus, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſus,</hi> and others, as hath been made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the World by many of the Reformed Writers, yea even by the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; witneſs <hi>Platina</hi> concerning the Lives
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152349:10"/>of the Popes, which <hi>Platina</hi> was the Popes own Library-keeper at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They can give no account what they mean by this Chair; for the material Chair can contribute nothing to the Popes Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility by any phyſical or internal vertue, elſe a Herds-man, if ſet upon this Infallible Chair, would be no leſs Infallible than the Pope himſelf: But by the formal or rather Moral Chair (in which ſenſe our Saviour makes mention of <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair) there can nothing elſe be underſtood than the Holy Scripture it ſelf; and if the Pope pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth according to the tenour thereof, we ſhall willingly hearken to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Holy Spirit, upon whom the Popes Infallibility is ſaid to depend, is not tyed to this or that place, but bloweth when, and where, and upon whom he liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>Others more ſharp-ſighted obſerving the fooliſhneſs of this diſtinction, have deviſed another; namely, that the Pope cannot erre in a queſtion of Right, though he may be deceived in matters of Fact. But this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is a broken Reed, upon which if a man lean, it will go into his hand and pierce it; although it was invented by the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152349:11"/>to heal that Wound which <hi>Alexnnder</hi> the VII. gave them, in that famous buſineſs of the five Articles. For firſt, when the Pope Anathematizeth a man, he conſiders him as believing ſo and ſo: Nor doth it appear, how he that is free from all poſſible errour, in matters of Right, can be ſubject to errour in matters of Fact; for when he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth concerning the ſenſe of any Book, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Infallible Interpreter of the ſenſe and meaning (which they do affirm) he may fall from a queſtion of Right into a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Fact; and ſo may determine that this and no other was the Authors meaning. 2. Seeing Law preſcribes to matter of Fact, it is not likely that he who is Infallible in matter of Right, can erre in matter of Fact. 3. Right doth ſometimes ariſe from Fact; therefore that which before was a queſtion of Fact, afterwards turning to a queſtion of Right, the Pope may give an infallible judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning it. 4. If this be true, the Pope cannot condemn nor Anathematize an Heretick, his judgment being fallible in matters of Fact. 5. We have before ſhortly proved, that the Pope hath erred moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably in matters of Right.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152349:11"/>
            <p>And thus you may ſee what difficulties they involve themſelves in, who place the Church and its Infallibility in the Pope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third and laſt Opinion of the Papiſts concerning the Church and its Infallibility, namely, that it conſiſts in the Pope and the Council together: But
<q>Incidit in Scyllam qui vult vitare Charybdim.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſame difficulties that were before propoſed, do preſs them equally: And moreover, theſe doubts will ariſe, Whether the Pope have his Infallibility from the Council, or the Council from the Pope? Whether if the Pope be abſent, his Legates have the ſame Infallibility that he himſelf would have, if Preſent? if ſo, whether he might not as eaſily Delegate this Infallibility to the Biſhops of the Council, as to his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates? Whether Decrees made in the Popes abſence be Infallible, and binding to the Conſcience? For if no Decrees be binding without the Popes Confirmation, it cannot be conceived, how he can extrajudicially (or out of Council) ratifie the Decrees made in Council, being the Popes Infallibility con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152349:12"/>not in his own Perſon, as ſeparate from, but joyntly with the Council.</p>
            <p>From what I have ſaid it evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Papiſts catch at a Shadow inſtead of the Body; and though they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately aſſert the Infallibility of their Church, yet they cannot agree, nor do they know where this Church is to be found: So that they are altogether ignorant how to ſatisfie a doubting Soul in this matter, and yet they deſiſt not
<q>Projicere ampullas &amp; ſeſquipedalia verba.</q>
            </p>
            <p>While I was yet in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I perceived my ſelf intangled in theſe Labaryinths, and often conſidered how to extricate my ſelf, that ſo I might with a clear Conſcience worſhip God in purity and holineſs. And although I had heard much in my own Country (which is <hi>Spain</hi>) of the Reformed Churches, yet I could never light on any of the Books of their Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, being forbidden to read them under the ſevereſt penalties. But hearing that they founded all their Doctrines upon the Holy Scriptures, I became very deſirous to ſearch into the ſame; (for in <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152349:12"/>the Clergy is not forbidden to read the Scriptures) and having met with theſe words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>All Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, that the Man of God may be perfect, thoroughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good works.</hi> It ſeemed to me, that the Apoſtle had drawn a lively Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture of a Miniſter of the Goſpel; and deſcribed at once what ought to be the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Fountain, as well as Method of Preaching; yea, and declared by what means the Man of God, that is, a Miniſter of Chriſt, may undoubtedly attain unto the full perfection of his Miniſtry, as well in reference to his own accompliſhments for the work, as to the good effects of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour upon the Souls committed to his care; namely, he aſſerteth, that the Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a rich Treaſure of Divine Knowledge, able to make a man wiſe unto Salvation, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. and pronounceth him accurſed that ſhould preach another Goſpel, even though it were an Angel from Heaven, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. but peace upon as many as walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. And God himſelf ſends his people to the Law, and to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152349:13"/>the Teſtimony, as the moſt effectual way to reduce them from ſeeking unto falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Wizards, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.19, 20.</p>
            <p>Having pondered theſe things ſeriouſly and often within my ſelf, and obſerved that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks ſo magnificent things of the Scriptures; and that he (who ſhunned not to declare the whole Counſel of God) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that he had ſaid no other things, than thoſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets did ſay ſhould come; I quickly concluded, that the only mark of the true Church, is to be taken from this Fountain, That the Church is built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and the chief Corner-ſtone is Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And I found that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (that glorious Light of Antiquity) did agree with me, writing, <hi>Contr. Ma. Arian. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Neither will I alledge the</hi> Nicene <hi>Chuncil to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, nor ought you to alledge the Council of</hi> Ariminum <hi>to mine: Let us not make uſe of Writings, partial to the one or to the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but of the holy Scriptures, that are impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judges of both; and compare Cauſe with Cauſe, Matter with Matter, and Reaſon with Reaſon.</hi> And elſewhere, writing againſt <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus, There</hi> (namely in the Scriptures) <hi>let us ſeek for the True Church; there let us diſcuſs the point.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152349:13"/>
            <p>Being now fully confirmed in this general Principle, I began to enquire narrowly into the Purity of particular Churches, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enquiry found, that none do ſo exactly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Scriptures, as the Reformed Churches: Wherefore I firmly reſolved with my ſelf, to forſake the <hi>Roman</hi> Idolatry, and aſſociate my ſelf to the Proteſtants: which I accordingly performed in <hi>France;</hi> and having renounced the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Superſtitions, I adjoyned my ſelf to the Reformed Church, as being the true Church of Chriſt; which I ſhall now ſhortly evince by the following Arguments.</p>
            <p>That is the true Church, which 1. Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates and maintains the Authority of the Scriptures. 2. Teacheth Doctrine agreeable to the Scriptures. 3. (Becauſe I will not be ſo Scripturary as to neglect the Teſtimony of the Fathers and Councils) Which agrees alſo with the Teſtimony of Ancient Fathers and Councils: But the Reformed Church is ſuch: Therefore the Reformed is the true Church.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, the Reformed Church maintains the Authority of the Scriptures againſt the Papiſts, who affirm, <hi>That the Scriptures have no Authority, as to us at leaſt,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152349:14"/>but from the Church.</hi> Which diſtinction was found out by <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> namely, that the Authority of the Scripture, conſidered in it ſelf, doth not depend upon the <hi>Church,</hi> but only in reſpect of us. But how frivolous is this diſtinction? For all Authority is Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and therefore it cannot be conſidered without a relation to us: And moreover the Suppoſition is falſe, that the Scriptures Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as to us, depends upon the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I come to overthrow this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, it will not be amiſs to obſerve, that the reaſon which induceth the Papiſts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, is evidently this; They know not how to anſwer the Proteſtants Arguments from Scripture, without wreſting the ſenſe; and therefore hold, that the ſenſe of the Scriptures depends upon the interpretation of the <hi>Church;</hi> which obligeth them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend, that the Authority of the Scriptures depends alſo upon the <hi>Church,</hi> being that, without the <hi>Churches</hi> Tradition, we can have no certainty of the Scriptures themſelves, nor of their ſenſe. In this they imitate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly the Ancient Hereticks, of whom <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſays, <hi>When the Hereticks are confuted from the Scriptures, they preſently begin to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Scriptures, as if they were not of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152349:14"/>Authority, or were otherwiſe written than they are cited by the Orthodox, and of which there is no certainty without Tradition.</hi> Where you may ſee an exact Portraicture of the Modern Papiſts.</p>
            <p>But to return to our purpoſe; we aſſert, That the Scriptures Authority doth no way depend upon the Authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> but of the Holy Ghoſt only, ſpeaking inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in our hearts, and externally in the Scriptures, becauſe he is their Author, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. and therefore he alone can give them their Authority. And as Chriſt ſeeks a Teſtimony from none beſides the Father; ſo neither doth his Word need any other, which he hath left upon Earth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of his own Perſon. And as it were very abſurd to affirm, that the Authority of the Kings Proclamation depends upon the Cryer, or a Rule upon the thing ruled, or that the Sun borrows his light from his own Orb or Vortex; ſo it is no leſs ridiculous to affirm, that the Authority of the Scriptures depends upon the <hi>Church:</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is the Candleſtick, the Word of God is the Candle, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.16. Now as a Candleſtick contributes nothing to the light of the Candle, ſo neither doth the <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152349:15"/>to the Authority of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>We reject not the Miniſterial Teſtimony of the <hi>Church</hi> in this affair, becauſe thereby we come to the knowledge of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt by the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Womans Teſtimony; which nevertheleſs was not the reaſon or ground of their Faith, but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument only.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts object, that the <hi>Church</hi> is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>the Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And from hence they conclude, that the Authority of the Scriptures, as to us, depends entirely upon the <hi>Church.</hi> But to paſs <hi>Camero</hi>'s obſervation, that theſe words belong to the ſixteenth verſe, where there is a Copulative Particle, which otherwiſe were uſeleſs; and that the Apoſtle firſt compares the <hi>Church</hi> to a Houſe, and then teacheth us, what is the chief Pillar of that Houſe, <hi>viz. God manifeſt in the Fleſh:</hi> For a Houſe cannot be called a Pillar, but a Pillar is in a Houſe. In this place <hi>Paul</hi> means not an <hi>Architectonical Pillar,</hi> (that ſuſtains the Authority of the Scriptures) but a <hi>Political,</hi> to which the F<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts of the Supreme Governour are affixed. Nor is <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Exception againſt this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of any weight, that the <hi>Church</hi> may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152349:15"/>be as well called a <hi>Bibliotheck,</hi> as a <hi>Pillar,</hi> in this ſenſe: For we affirm, that the <hi>Church</hi> doth not only keep theſe Books, but alſo teach and publiſh the Contents thereof, and expoſe them to the view of the people.</p>
            <p>So then, the Teſtimony of the <hi>Church</hi> may be one Motive to induce us to believe the Divine Authority of the Scriptures, but cannot beget in our minds a firm and certain perſwaſion of it, which is the work of the Holy Ghoſt only, whom God joyns with his Word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. <hi>My Spirit which is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks well to this purpoſe, in his Confeſſions; <hi>But how ſhall I know that theſe are thy words?</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid ſo indeed, but</hi> Moſes <hi>is gone; and if he were preſent, and ſhould ſpeak Hebrew, I could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him; but if he ſpoke Latin, and I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood him, how could I be certain that he ſpoke the truth? The Truth it ſelf, which is neither Greck, Latin, Hebrew, nor Barbarian, without any ſound of the tongue, or noiſe of Syllables, would ſay unto me inwardly in the Cabinet of my heart, he ſpeaketh truth.</hi> You ſee, Chriſtian Readers, how <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was perſwaded of the Divinity of the Scriptures,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152349:16"/>not by the Authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> nor of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, but by the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Truth ſpeaking in his heart, which is the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>It's in vain to reply hereunto, that every one may pretend the Spirit; for pretenſions cannot prejudice the Truth; the Queſtion between us and the Papiſts is not, <hi>Whether the Scriptures are of Divine Authority, or not?</hi> for both of us aſſert that they are: But, <hi>Whether he that admits this, is perſwaded of it?</hi> To which whether they or we give the moſt ſatisfactory anſwer, we leave the whole Chriſtian World, that are not partial to either Party, to judge.</p>
            <p>We conclude therefore, that as this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Whether the Scriptures are the Word of God?</hi> is unworthy of a Chriſtian: So Jeſuit <hi>Sambays</hi>'s Aſſertion <hi>(de fide Orthodoxa)</hi> is fooliſh and ridiculous, <hi>That the Proteſtants have not the Scriptures.</hi> For, beſides that, he defends it for no other end, but that he may ſhun the dint of their Arguments drawn from the Scriptures: He uſeth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Medium</hi> to prove that Aſſertion, but that the Reformed <hi>Church,</hi> wanting the Marks of the true <hi>Church,</hi> is a falſe <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore cannot have the Scriptures,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152349:16"/>which do both in their matter and form de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the <hi>Church:</hi> Which Argument is moſt falſe, and doth manifeſtly beg the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Scriptures, and their ſenſe, depend upon the Authority of the <hi>Church;</hi> which we utterly deny, and that not without reaſon, as I ſhewed above. Moreover, the Jeſuit ſheweth his <hi>Cauſe</hi> to be deſperate, by endeavouring to rob us of the Scriptures; for none of the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers denied the Scriptures to any Heretick that argued his own Cauſe from them; and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that we quoted above, affirms, that the Scriptures are not peculiar to any one Party, but impartial Judges of all. We might with far better reaſon return this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument upon the Papiſts, becauſe we have proved, that their <hi>Repreſentative Church</hi> is not only falſe, but no <hi>Church</hi> at all: But I am not ſo much afraid of their Arguments from Scripture, and therefore do not deny them the Bible.</p>
            <p>Having eſtabliſhed the Opinion of the Reformed <hi>Churches,</hi> in reference to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scriptures, I ſhall now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the properties of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore I affirm, <hi>that the Scriptures are perfect,</hi> by a perfection of parts as well
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152349:17"/>as degrees; <hi>and ſo ſufficient to Salvation,</hi> Pſal. 19. <hi>The Law of God is perfect:</hi> Their ſufficiency appears from the forecited place, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>The acceſſion of the New Teſtament to the Old, doth not diſprove the perfection and ſufficiency of the Scriptures: For he that revealed the whole Counſel of God to Believers, did nevertheleſs reveal no other than what <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before, as we hinted above. Hence the Ancient Fathers ſaid very well, <hi>As the New Teſtament is hid in the Old, ſo the Old is made plain and clear in the New.</hi> Nor doth a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in degree alter the nature or <hi>ſpecies</hi> of a thing; neither is the Queſtion betwixt the Papiſts and us, concerning this or that part of the Scriptures, but concerning the whole Canon, as it was received by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Church,</hi> and enumerated by <hi>Hierom.</hi> So that in this Argument there is evidently the Fallacy of dividing what ought to be joyned together.</p>
            <p>And as we juſtly cut off the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Books from this perfection and ſufficiency of the Scriptures, becauſe they contradict both themſelves and the Canon; nor were they ever received in the <hi>Jewiſh Church, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152349:17"/>which the Oracles of God were committed,</hi> Rom. 3.2. So we reject the Popiſh diſtinction of Protocanonical &amp; Deuterocanonical Books, with the ſame facility that they propoſe it, being without proof.</p>
            <p>Hence we do but little eſteem <hi>unwritten Traditions,</hi> becauſe what is written doth ſufficiently inſtruct us what we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and do in order to life eternal, <hi>John</hi> 20.31.</p>
            <p>It's ridiculous to refer the ſeveral Orders of Monks, and particularly the ſhaving of their Crowns, to theſe unwritten Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; becauſe Chriſt ſays, <hi>I have yet many things to ſay unto you, but you cannot bear them now, Joh.</hi> 16.12. For if this had been the thing that Chriſt had further to ſay unto them, he might eaſily have ſent for a Barber and cauſed their Heads to be ſhaved: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the Monks, (<hi>whoſe duty was to weep, and not to teach,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierom</hi>) were ſhaven as a ſign of their penitence, not of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or preeminence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Scriptures are plain and eaſie to be underſtood; <hi>The Commandment, enlightning the eyes,</hi> Pſal. 19.8. <hi>Whatſoever things were written afore-time, were written for our learning, that we through patience and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152349:18"/>comfort of the Scriptures might have hope, Rom.</hi> 15.4. Thoſe things therefore which are abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, being very few, and very eaſie, are clearly and plainly ſet down in the Scriptures, though other things not ſo abſolutely neceſſary may puzle the moſt Sagacious underſtandings: <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays well; <hi>The holy Scriptures are ſuch that a Lamb may wade in them, and yet an Elephant may ſwim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then that the Scriptures are plain, as is evident from Reaſon, and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Fathers, the Reformed <hi>Churches</hi> do with good reaſon attribute a judgment of diſcretion, in Controverſies of Faith, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true Chriſtian: So that every Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, by frequent reading and comparing of the Scriptures, may eaſily underſtand their meaning, at leaſt as to things abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation; <hi>For no Propheſie of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y private interpretation, nor came by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.20, 21.</p>
            <p>As for the Fathers of the Ancient <hi>Church,</hi> and the four Primitive Councils, we willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imbrace them as Interpreters of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; yea moreover, we affirm, that in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152349:18"/>ſubordination to the Scriptures, they may bind, but not force our belief: But we ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny, that the Fathers, or theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, or the Pope, are Judges of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies about matters of Faith; but the only Judge of all ſuch Controverſies is the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking in the Scriptures, or as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, Chriſt himſelf; <hi>Let Chriſt judge of this Controverſie, who although he be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in his Perſon, yet is preſent in his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it doth appear that the Scriptures may rightly be called a Normal Judge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding the queſtion in manner of a Law, though not outwardly proclaiming the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: <hi>The Word of God is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, Heb.</hi> 4.12. We have ſufficiently proved, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Churches</hi> do vindicate the Authority and Properties of the Scriptures: It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains now to be proved, that they teach ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs the Doctrines of God, and his Attributes of the Trinity, and the like, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is little difference between the Papiſts and us in there Points, except in ſome Preter-fundamental things, which the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Dominicans</hi> do alſo diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves. I ſhall now only take notice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152349:19"/>of this, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> do very abſurdly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine <hi>Free-will,</hi> viz. <hi>A Faculty whereby all things requiſite to action being preſent, the will may act or not act, act this or the contrary.</hi> For beſides that, when the Object is preſent to the Underſtanding, the Will is neceſſarily determined by the laſt practical judgment of the underſtanding to imbrace or reject the object; like as if Straw and Fire come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there muſt needs a Flame be kindled: I ſay, beſides this, it's impoſſible for any man to alter the Preſcience and Decree of God (which is one of the things requiſite to action) <hi>for the Counſel of God ſtands, and he will do all his pleaſure.</hi> All things requiſite to <hi>Judas</hi> his betraying of Chriſt being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, (<hi>viz.</hi> the laſt practical judgment of his underſtanding, the receiving of the Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Eternal Counſel of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning that Chriſt ſhould be delivered into the hands of men, ſuffer death, and riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the third day) it was impoſſible for him not to act.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Reformed <hi>Churches</hi> do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently define Free-will; <hi>A faculty of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freely, without compulſion, or phyſical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination to one thing.</hi> For the Will cannot be forced to any elicite or internal act; nor
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152349:19"/>is it capable of a phyſical or natural neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, determining it to one thing, as Fire is determined to burn. But it is not free from the determination of the Divine Decree, and the laſt practical judgment of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; nor in the unregenerate from ſin, to which it is in general neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by its Original depravation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it hath a freedom to chuſe this or that ſpecial ſin: So that in the unregenerate man it is free only to will, nor can he by his own ſtrength perform any action ſpiritually good: <hi>Of our ſelves, as of our ſelves, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think a good thought,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. much leſs do a good action by nature. <hi>We are dead in ſin,</hi> Eph. 2.1. <hi>without God in the world,</hi> Eph. 2.3. <hi>and every imagination of our heart is only evil continually,</hi> Gen. 6.5. And the beſt actions that the unregenerate can do, are really evil, becauſe they do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Faith; and <hi>whatſoever is not of Faith, is ſin,</hi> Rom. 14.23. So that as from a total privation there is no returning to the habit, but by an Infinite Power; ſo from ſin, which is a privation of that rectitude, which ought to be in our faculties and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is no returning to righteouſneſs, except God do quicken us from the Dead;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152349:20"/>and ſay to us as unto <hi>Lazarus,</hi> Lazarus <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, Joh.</hi> 11.43. and cauſe the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to ariſe in the dark Horizon of our hearts, ſaying as in the firſt Creation, <hi>Let there be light, Gen.</hi> 1. And truly ſeeing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, according to Scripture phraſe, is a new Creation, (<hi>Create in me a clean heart,</hi> Pſa. 51. <hi>We are his workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works,</hi> Eph. 2.10. <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but the New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Gal.</hi> 6.15.) it cannot be the work of leſs than an Infinite Power, whereby God <hi>worketh in us both to will and to do of his good preaſure, Phil.</hi> 2.13. So that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did rightly affirm, that the good works of the Heathen were but gliſtering ſins: They may indeed act ſomething that is morally good, by the general influence of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; yet they can act nothingthat is truly good in a Theological ſenſe, becauſe they want Faith to purifie their hearts, nor do they aim at the glory of God; for they do not ſhun this or that ſin ſimply becauſe it is a ſin, but from a vain-glorious deſire of Reputation among the people.</p>
            <p>Hence it followeth, that Juſtification and Sanctification are not ours, but Gods: ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152349:20"/>that when God conferreth Glory upon thoſe that are Juſtified and Sanctified, he may with good reaſon be ſaid to Crown with this reward his own gifts, and not our works. As for Juſtification, of which we intend to ſpeak firſt, it is twofold, active and paſſive; for it may be conſidered either in reſpect of God that juſtifieth, or of Man that is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. In the former conſideration it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an act of God, whereby he abſolves the ſinner, and reputes him righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for the Merits and ſatisfaction of Chriſt. Hence God is ſaid to <hi>juſtifie the ungodly,</hi> Rom. 4.5. <hi>by his grace, through the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 3.24. So that God in juſtifying maketh no phyſical change in the ſinner, as the Papiſts ſay, who would have the Juſtification of God to be of the ſame nature with Tranſubſtantiation, whereby one thing is changed into another; that is, that God in Juſtifying doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as a Judge, pronouncing one at the Bar Innocent, but as it were by a phyſical im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, making a righteous man out of an unrighteous, even as Chriſt turned water into Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine, Becan,</hi> and other Jeſuits, have laboured much in the proof of this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152349:21"/>but without any ſucceſs: They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce nothing from Scripture, but what is to be referred to Sanctification, not Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And thus they commit the fallacy of <hi>ignoratio Elenchi;</hi> and as for their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from Reaſon, they are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, that they do not deſerve a Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Their chief Argument is taken from the Word it ſelf; for, ſay they, to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie,</hi> according to the Etimology of the word, is nothing elſe but <hi>to make juſt or righteous,</hi> being it is compounded of <hi>juſtus</hi> and <hi>facio;</hi> as well as to Sanctifie is to make, not to pronounce holy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore to juſtifie cannot import the abſolution of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner who is really unrighteous, but the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of him righteous. But they hereby ſhew themſelves to be no better Gramarians than they are Divines; for the ſenſe of a word, in matters of Faith, is not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Calepine,</hi> but from the Word of God, which is the Rule of our Faith. Now it is manifeſt, and hath been demonſtrated by many, that Juſtification is every where in the Scriptures taken in a <hi>Law-ſenſe.</hi> Thus Solomon, <hi>He that juſtifieth the ungodly, and condemneth the righteous, are both an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the Lord.</hi> Here the juſtifying of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152349:21"/>the unrighteous is oppoſed to the condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the righteous; and ſo in all other places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if this were the meaning of the word <hi>Juſtifie,</hi> then there would be no difference between Juſtification and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; which nevertheleſs is evident from Rev. 22.11. <hi>He that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill; and he that is holy, let him be holy ſtill.</hi> Alſo Rom. 8.30. <hi>Whom he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, them he alſo glorified:</hi> where under the word <hi>Glorifie</hi> is comprehended <hi>Sanctification,</hi> which is begun <hi>Glory,</hi> even as <hi>Glory</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, This Compoſition with the Verb <hi>Facio</hi> doth not always import an internal change, as appears from the Song of the Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>My Soul doth magnifie the Lord.</hi> Now let them ſet their heads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and prove, that the Bleſſed Virgin, by magnifying the Lord, did cauſe any inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal change in him; and we ſhall alſo allow, that God by juſtifying us, doth make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal change in us;
<q>Ante leves vero paſcentur in aethere cervi.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto of Active Juſtification: Now
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152349:22"/>we ſhall come to treat of Paſſive Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Juſtification conſidered in reſpect of the man juſtified. And thus it is nothing elſe, but an aſſured conſidence of our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in Chriſt, and by the imputation of his Merits, which we receive and apply unto our ſelves by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26. Hence it appears, that the Meritorious Cauſe of our Juſtification is the Merit of Chriſt, as we proved a little before; and the hand by which we apply this ſatisfaction of our Saviour, or the inſtrumental cauſe of our Juſtification, is Faith. <hi>Man is juſtified by faith, without the works of the Law,</hi> Rom. 3.28. It is as clear from the Scriptures as the light of the Sun in mid-day, that we are juſtified by faith only: <hi>By grace ye are ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves, it is the gift of God, Eph.</hi> 2.8. So that I ſhall inſiſt no longer upon this point, but conclude with the Apoſtle, <hi>That by the deeds of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified, for by the Law is the knowledge of ſin,</hi> Rom. 3.20. There is therefore no Juſtification in the ſight of God by our works, but only by ſaith, which applieththe <hi>Panacea</hi> of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto our dead hearts, and cauſeth us to live in God, and God in us.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152349:22"/>
            <p>We are not ſo unreaſonable, as to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Works from Faith; yet nevertheleſs we affirm, that Faith only doth juſtifie: it's the eye only that ſees, the hand only that weighs; yet neither can the eye ſee, nor the hand weigh, unleſs they be united to the body: Even ſo Faith only doth juſtifie; but this Faith is never ſeparated from Good Works.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> indeed ſaith, <hi>We are juſtified by works, and not by faith only,</hi> Jam. 2.24. But he either means juſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, as in the eighteenth verſe, <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works;</hi> or elſe the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of internal faith by external actions; or elſe he ſpeaks by a <hi>Metonimy</hi> of the <hi>effect</hi> for the <hi>cauſe;</hi> ſo that by faith and works he means a working faith; which ſeems to agree well with the words, <hi>You ſee then how that by works man is juſtified, and not by faith only;</hi> that is, not by a ſolitary or naked faith, which is not accompanied with works, <hi>for faith being alone is dead;</hi> but by a living faith, which ſhews its foundneſs by works.</p>
            <p>So that we are not juſtified by works, but by faith only; and whoſoever will narrowly look into himſelf and his own frailty, muſt needs break forth into <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s words;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152349:23"/>
               <hi>Becauſe of the frailty of humane life, and the uncertainty of our own righteouſneſs, it is ſafeſt to relye only upon the mercy of God,</hi> Bel. de bon. oper. Conſider, Candid Reader, the words of this Cardinal, who (as I can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, if need be) at the end of the greateſt Controverſies between us and the Papiſts, yields at laſt unto the truth, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, though an <hi>Italian,</hi> to be more a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant than a Papiſt.</p>
            <p>Thus we have proved, by Gods aſſiſtance, that Active Juſtification is an external judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial abſolution of an unrighteous man, and pronouncing of him righteous; and that Paſſive Juſtification is by faith only, and that a living faith, which applieth to us the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>As for Sanctification, I ſhall ſay little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, by reaſon the Papiſts don't diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree much with the Proteſtants in this Point, as to the nature of the thing; only I utterly deny, that the good works which we do are meritorious, or neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>neceſſuate medii,</hi> as a mean to bring us to Salvation: <hi>Bernard</hi> ſays well, <hi>Good works are the way to the Kingdom, not the cauſe of reigning:</hi> nor does the Popiſh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction between <hi>merit</hi> of <hi>congruity</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152349:23"/>
               <hi>condignity:</hi> mitigate this Aſſertion for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the Congruity of Gods Reward for our Works conſiſts onely in his own good pleaſure; <hi>Fear not little Flock, for it is your Father's good pleaſure to give you a Kingdom, Luk.</hi> 12.32. I have often admired, that they have found no Text of Scripture to prove the condignity of works, but this one which is Diametrically contrary to their Aſſertion. <hi>The Sufferings of this preſent time are not worthy (but condign) to be compared with the Glory that is to be revealed in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the onely place where the word <hi>condignus</hi> is to be found.</p>
            <p>I will proceed now to ſhew how found and genuine the Doctrine of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is concerning the Sacraments, which are <hi>Seals of the righteouſneſs of faith, Rom.</hi> 4.11. And ſhortly refute the Popiſh Errours. As for Baptiſm, both Parties acknowledge it to be a Sacrament of Initiation, by which in the faith of our Parents (which is my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) we are implanted into the Church, which is the Body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Papiſts</hi> falſely affirm, that Baptiſm <hi>ex opere operato</hi> (by vertue of the work wrought) works in us Regeneration, and aboliſhes Original Sin: Not onely becauſe an
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152349:24"/>external, corporal thing can have no influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon things internal and ſpiritual, in reference to the rectifying thereof, which can onely be done by God himſelf; <hi>every good and perfect Gift comes down from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lights,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James:</hi> But likewiſe becauſe the ſign of the Covenant cannot communicate to us the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Covenant.</p>
            <p>And the contrary appears alſo from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; becauſe thoſe that have been baptized, are and have been ſubject to everlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if this Sacrament <hi>ex opere opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> did work Grace, Regeneration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then <hi>Abraham</hi> could not have been reputed <hi>righteous by faith in uncircumciſion, Rom.</hi> 4.9. Moreover in the Primitive Times, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to them that were baptized when come to Age, Faith was required before the Seal of Righteouſneſs were ſtampt upon their hearts and conſciences. Now becauſe Faith is the Root of the reſt of the Graces, and hath annexed unto it that great work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: It neceſſarily follows, that the Apoſtle requiring faith in the Adult, did ſuppoſe the reſt of the Graces to be in them, not imagining that they ſhould be conferred upon them, but rather ſealed or confirmed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152349:24"/>by Baptiſm: for Baptiſm is a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith; and not a thing that by its internal vertue work Faith and Regeneration.</p>
            <p>For this very reaſon, <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and other of the Fathers affirmed, that Infants are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the Faith of their Parents, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents; or in the Faith of the Church, if their Parents were unknown, or Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; becauſe they were perſwaded, that Faith is rather required before, than confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Baptiſm. So that we believe that the holy Ghoſt doth operate in the tender hearts and minds of elect Infants, even from their Birth, and that effectually, though inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: and although perhaps he doth not work in them ſubjectively an actual faith; yet he objectively applies unto them the benefits of Chriſt, which in others are received by an actual faith,</p>
            <p>But leſt any ſhould think that we falſely charge our Adverſaries with this Aſſertion; I will ſhew the candid Reader the reaſon why they aſſert it; and then evince the ſame from a cuſtom frequent among them in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why they affirm it, is becauſe they hold that Infants departing without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152349:25"/>cannot be ſaved, but go into the <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Infantum</hi> (a kind of Hole prepared to put Children into) where they ſuffer <hi>paenam damni,</hi> but not <hi>paenam ſeaſus;</hi> that is, they are deprived of the Beatifick Viſion of God, though they are not under any ſenſible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If then their Election, which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and their being under the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, which belongeth to them as well as to their Parents, be not ſufficient to ſave them becauſe they were not baptized; ſurely Baptiſm which maketh them capable to demand Heaven, muſt by a phyſical vertue work thoſe Graces, whereby they may attain unto Salvation. (2.) They hold that none can be ſaved without the Boſom of the Church; and that none can be reputed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, except ſuch as have been baptized. Moreover their Cuſtom is to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of the Baptiſm of Women (providing the Form be obſerved) in caſe of neceſſity; which ſhews how abſolutely neceſſary they eſteem Baptiſm unto Salvation.</p>
            <p>Having proved the Charge, <hi>I</hi> ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Errour.</p>
            <p>And firſt it is as certain, That all Infants departing without Baptiſm are not deprived of the beatifick Viſion; as that <hi>David</hi> was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152349:25"/>ſaved, who after death was to go to his Child that died without Circumciſion (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18, 23.) in place whereof Baptiſm ſucceeded, as appears from <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.11, 12. And as certain, as that the promiſe of Eternal Life doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Infants; which Argument is of the ſame force againſt the Anabaptiſts, that deny the Seal to Infants, to whom the promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, (for which reaſon <hi>Peter</hi> did willingly confer Baptiſm upon ſome Converts (<hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39) as againſt the Papſts, that deny Eternal Life to Children dying without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, although they be under the promiſe and Covenant of Grace; for he that is under the Covenant of Grace, or the Promiſes, is in Chriſt; and he that is in Chriſt will certainly be ſaved: Therefore Children being under the Covenant of Grace, and the Promiſe of Life, will certainly be ſaved, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>But they object this Scripture, <hi>Except a man be born of water, and of the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, Joh.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. whence they conclude that none can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>But <hi>I</hi> anſwer, that nothing elſe is meant by this water and ſpirit but the holy Ghoſt himſelf, who is compared to water, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152349:26"/>he waſheth away our ſins. There is another expreſſion like unto this in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>He ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire;</hi> that is, the Holy Ghoſt ſhall purge you as fire doth Gold, ſeven times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined. So that theſe Expreſſions are Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical and Figurative: <hi>Virgil</hi> hath the like expreſſion:
<q>— Pateris libamus &amp; auro</q>
            </p>
            <p>We drink out of Cups and Gold, that is out of Golden Cups; ſo to be baptized with the Spirit, and with fire, is nothing elſe but to be baptized with a fiery Spirit; and the ſame way are Chriſt's words concerning wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſpirit to be underſtood; wherefore what he ſaith here figuratively, by way of <hi>Hendiadis</hi> he expreſſed in the third Verſe in proper words, <hi>except a man be born again he can not ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi> So that it clearly appears from Chriſts own expoſition, that here is underſtood ſpiritual Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not the external waſhing with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We utterly deny that Baptiſm by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men is valid, and not to be reiterated.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152349:26"/>
            <p>They can only alledge the example of <hi>Zipporah</hi> that Circumciſed her Son; whence they argue, that a Woman may as lawfully Baptize, as Circumciſe. I ſhall not give the anſwer that is uſual amongſt ſome Divines, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Zipporah</hi> ſinned in ſo doing, for God never bleſſeth men for any ſin, as ſuch; but he did bleſs <hi>Moſes</hi> for this action of <hi>Zipporah.</hi> But I anſwer thus, that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion in the Old Teſtament was indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred by any perſon, by reaſon it was not ſo ſtrictly joyned with the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Office of Preaching, as Baptiſm is in the New Teſtament; <hi>Go and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. So that now it is unlawful for any to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Baptiſm, but ſuch as are ordained for the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall proceed to ſpeak of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacrament (without regarding the reſt of their five Sacraments, that have no ground in the Scriptures, nor the Fathers) which is the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>According to ſound Doctrine, the Lords Supper is nothing elſe but a viſible ſign of an inviſible Grace; wherein by receiving of Bread and Wine, is ſignified our receiving of the Body and Blood of Chriſt as a Seal
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152349:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Covenant of Crace, tending to our Salvation. We deny not, that the Body and Blood of Chriſt is really preſent in this holy Sacrament; but we deny, 1. That it is corporally preſent, becauſe it is circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptive, and in Heaven, and therefore cannot be every where. 2. We deny, that the Lords Supper is a Sacrifice for the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and the Dead; which point I ſhall chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſt upon.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, the Papiſts do very much urge their Tranſubſtantiation, by which they underſtand nothing elſe but the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral preſence of the Body and Blood of our Saviour, under the appearance and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of Bread and Wine, imagining that the ſubſtance of the Bread and Wine is turned to the firſt nothing, out of which it was created, and the accidents only do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main which affect our ſenſes of ſight, feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and taſte: The falſhood and abſurdity of this imagination I thus demonſtrate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Neither the Word nor the thing is to be found in Scripture; for after the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration it is called, <hi>the Bread of which we are partakers,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. Now if the Bread were annihilated, how could we be partakers of it? And moreover, no Papiſt will allow
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152349:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>that it be called Bread after Conſecration, which yet we ſee the Scripture doth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Word it ſelf is new, and was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of before the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, when <hi>Berengarius</hi> was forced to recant the Truth, and fall into a moſt abominable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, namely, that Chriſts Body is bruiſed by the Teeth, and let down into the Belly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Word is no way adapted to the thing; yea, Creation may be as well called Annihilation, as this may be called Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation; for Tranſubſtantiation is nothing elſe, but a mutation or turning of one ſubſtance into another; as in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> Wine was turned into Water: but the Papiſts ſay, that in this caſe one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is not turned into another, but that the one (namely, the Bread and Wine) is annihilated, and the other, namely, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Chriſt, is induced, under the appearance and accidents of Bread and Wine (although they have a thouſand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions here about the introducing of the Body and Blood of Chriſt under theſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, which I ſhall paſs over;) ſo that it ought rather to be called, <hi>an Annihilation of one ſubſtance, and Introduction of another:</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152349:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>but an abſurd name is fit enough for ſuch an abſurd thing.</p>
            <q>Conveniunt rebus nominal ſaepe ſuis.</q>
            <p n="4">4. The thing which is diſtributed in the Sacrament, is called by the Ancients a Sign and a Figure of Chriſts Body. Now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be a Sign or a Figure of it ſelf: therefore Chriſt cannot be Corporally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord was pleaſed to ſay, this is my Body, when he gave but the figure of his Body.</hi> And moſt of the Ancient Fathers do underſtand the words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo the Scriptures call it, <hi>A Seal of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith,</hi> as we ſaid before; now the Seal cannot be the thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It were too tedious to conſider all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Papiſts againſt the Doctrine of the Reformed Churches, concerning the Lords Supper, only this one I cannot paſs by, which I have read in an Anonymous Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, whereby he endeavours to invalidate our laſt reaſon againſt Tranſubſtantiation, by giving this inſtance, that <hi>David</hi> might have been a ſign of himſelf, as ſighting with <hi>Goliah,</hi> if he had preſented himſelf to the peoples view upon a Theater.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152349:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But I anſwer, 1. <hi>David</hi> had not been in that caſe a ſign of himſelf, but of the actions he performed in the Combat.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>David</hi> had been ſowed up in a Sack, or laid himſelf down upon the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter covered with an Aſſes skin (as they ſay Chriſt's Body is covered with the accidents of Bread and Wine) ſo that he could not be ſeen, I do not underſtand how he could have been a ſign of himſelf, or his actions either. I ſhall omit to obſerve, that the Sacrament was inſtituted in Commemoration of the Man Chriſt, &amp; a that Commemoration is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of abſent perſons; as likewiſe many of their Exceptions againſt, us for brevities ſake.</p>
            <p>Only I ſhall ſhortly demonſtrate the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is not a Sacrifice for the ſins of the Living and the Dead, by this general argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Where there is no Prieſt, no Altar, no proper Hoſt, there can be no proper Sacrifice for ſin: But in the New Teſtament there is none of theſe (beſide Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Major is moſt certain; for Relatives are mutual, and the one preſuppoſeth the other: therefore where there is a proper Sacrifice, there
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152349:29"/>muſt be an Altar, a Prieſt, and an Hoaſt, properly ſo called. So <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> himſelf ſaith, That <hi>Altars uſe not to be Erected, unleſs for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, properly ſo called. (de Miſs. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 16.) And elſewhere, <hi>without an Altar can be no Sacrifice, de Cult San. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Now to prove the Minor; there is no material Altar to be found in the Scriptures, as one to be uſed in the New Teſtament. Chriſt who inſtituted this Sacrament, Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame on the <hi>Table, Luk.</hi> 22.21. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. But there is no mention made of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, which had been certainly done, if an Altar had been in uſe: Hence the great <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſays (<hi>de Miſs. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17.) <hi>The Apoſtles did not uſe the Names of Prieſthood, Sacrifice, Altar;</hi> as knowing well there could be none after the material Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152349:29"/>were Sealed up: But the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts object, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. <hi>We have an Altar whereof they have no right to eat, which ſerve the Tabernacle.</hi> I anſwer, This Text ſpeaketh of an improper, figurative, inviſible Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, but we deny onely a proper and material Altar: for that the words are figurative, evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, becauſe no Body can eat of a material Altar: And moreover, the Sacrifice that the Apoſtle would have to be offered up upon it, doth plainly diſcover what kind of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar he means: <hi>By him therefore let us offer the Sacrifice of Praiſe to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually; that is the fruit of our Lips, giving Thanks to his Name.</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers alſo do agree with us. <hi>None of theſe is viſible, neither the Prieſt, nor the Sacrifice, nor the Altar; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> in Epiſt. <hi>ad Heb. I think that the Altar is nothing elſe but the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Lord; Bernard,</hi> in Serm. 4.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152349:30"/>
               <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls it <hi>the Altar which is above, Orat.</hi> 24. And finally the Papiſts themſelves are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that here is meant an improper Altar; <hi>I do not urge the place it ſelf. Bell. de Miſs. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14. as alſo <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Anſelmus,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor is there any proper Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the New Teſtament. For <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> propheſieth, That <hi>the Sacrifice and Oblation ſhall ceaſe:</hi> And we ſee this Propheſie fulfilled; The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nor yet that he ſhould offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf often, but now once in the end of the World,</hi> Heb. 9.26. <hi>Every Prieſt ſtandeth daily miniſtring and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; but this man after he had offered one Sacrifice for ſins, for ever, ſat down on the right hand of God,</hi> Heb. 10.12. where the Apoſtle evidently aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that Chriſt offered himſelf but once; and doth not offer himſelf, nor can he be ſo offered, again. Yea the Apoſtle urgeth the ſufficiency
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152349:30"/>of Sacrifice by theſe two Arguments. (1.) Becauſe he offered himſelf but once, and did not repeat his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as inſufficient. (2) Becauſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perfected his Work, he ſat down on the right hand of God for ever: But the Prieſts did always ſtand, which ſignifyed that they had not yet compleated their Work, but muſt lay their hands once more to it, before they might ſit down and reſt from their work, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Papiſts deviſing daily Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of Chriſt after that one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, doth derogate from its ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and makes Chriſt lyable to the Miniſtry of ſtanding, who is already ſet down for ever at the right hand of God. This was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the reaſon why God deſtroyed <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Temple (after Chriſts Mediatory Office was fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to one part of his Prieſthood, namely his Sacrifice) that there might
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152349:31"/>be no more material Sacrifices, that being the place to which they were confined.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts urge the Cuſtom of the Ancients, and the expreſſions of the Fathers, who ſpeak very oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of Sacrifices. But it is clear, that the Fathers meant no other, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Sacrifica Euchariſtica</hi> Sacrifices of a Thanksgiving, which were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly performed at the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; which with Prayers and Alms are indeed a <hi>living Sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God, Rom.</hi> 12.1. Hence <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> ſaith, <hi>that a righteous Soul is a holy Altar, and holy Prayer is the Incenſe. Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius</hi> ſaith, <hi>two things are to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, a Gift and a Sacrifice, both incorporcal; integrity of mind is the gift; Prayer, and Pſalms are the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Augustin</hi> calls our heart an Altar, Humility and Praiſe a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and Charity the Fire. So
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152349:31"/>
               <hi>ronimus, Ambroſius</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>As for the Prieſt, there is none beſides Chriſt; for he is a Prieſt for ever, <hi>after the Order of Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zedek;</hi> and Levitical Prieſts they cannot be, being that Order is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>Thus having proved, that there is no Altar, Prieſt, nor Hoaſt, beſides Chriſt himſelf, <hi>who is our Sacrifice, our Prieſt, and our Altar, Epiphan. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>com.</hi> 1. <hi>hoereſ.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there is now no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sacrifice for the ſins of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and the Dead; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence no Tranſubſtantiation, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which this Sacrifice is builded.</p>
            <p>And here their Purgatory falls to the Ground; for beſides that it is contrary to Scriptures, to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to the Antient Fathers, and injurious to the ſatisfaction and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt; moreover, if there be no Sacrifice, there can be no Maſs,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152349:32"/>and by conſequence no money for the delivery of Souls out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
            <p>Here alſo falls to the ground their Doctrine of Concomitancy, for the ſake whereof, (as <hi>Gelatius</hi> one of their Popes Intimates) they have committed Sacriledg, in the Cup from the Laity; which although the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> confeſſeth to be contrary to the Primitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, and Cuſtom of the Antient Church; yet for ſome ridiculous reaſons (ſuch as; That ſome perſons hands do ſhake, that ſome have deformed Whiskers and Beards) pronouncing an Anathema a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that will contradict it.</p>
            <p>And I have many times wondred why by the ſame Doctrine of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitancy, they may not as well give the Cup, and take away the Bread, or take away the Cup from the Clergy as well as the Laity?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152349:32"/>Why it is a fufilling of the Law to abſtain from the one, and a ſin, yea a mortal ſin to abſtain from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>There is neither reaſon nor Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to countenance it in the leaſt. So that the Reformed Churches teach ſound Doctrine, both as to the Nature, and the Integrity of this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The laſt Point I ſhall touch upon, is the <hi>worſhipping of Saints.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants agree herein with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the Ancient Fathers, that the Saints are to be honoured by imitation, but not to be religiouſly adored; and that for theſe three Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We cannot believe in Saints, therefore we cannot worſhip them, <hi>how ſhall they call on him, in whom
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152349:33"/>they have not believed?</hi> Rom. 10.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are ſeverely forbidden to worſhip any but God: <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> Mat. 4.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Saints do not know our thoughts, nor can they hear our Prayers: <hi>Abraham is ignorant of us, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledgeth us not.</hi> Iſa. 63.16. Hence <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>To know the thoughts of the heart, is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of God:</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>The Angels know not the ſecrets of the heart.</hi> And again, <hi>to know the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thoughts and actions of men, is above the perfection of a create un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> And <hi>Durandus</hi> denies that the glorified Saints do know our thoughts. Finally <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the dead know not what is done here. God onely knoweth the hearts of the Children of Men,</hi> 1 Kings 8.39.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152349:33"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, though a Saint, would not ſuffer <hi>Cornelius</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, ſaying <hi>I my ſelf alſo am a man,</hi> Acts 10.26. nor would the Angel ſuffer <hi>John</hi> to preſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him: <hi>worſhip God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. Yea a Heathen Poet could tell that God onely is to be worſhipped.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſum, dixit, nec ſacro thuris honore</l>
               <l>Humanum dignare capu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Their diſtinction betwixt <hi>latria,</hi> and <hi>dulia,</hi> and <hi>hyperdulia</hi> hath been abundantly refuted by many of the Reformed Writers.</p>
            <p>I ſhall onely conclude, that if Papiſts cannot be accuſed of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Idolatry, yet they are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty of material Idolatry.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:152349:34"/>
            <p>Having demonſtrated, that the Proteſtant Churches do defend the Holy Scriptures, and conform their Doctrine thereunto in the moſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty points. I juſtly infer, that <hi>the Proteſtant Church is a true, faithful, and ſincere Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhut up all with this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that the Papiſts percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that they cannot prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtants in diſputing of their Doctrine: They queſtion the Proteſtant Mineſtery as not Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate. But beſides that their own Scholaſticks (as <hi>Bannes, Canus &amp;c.</hi>) do allow, that the power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining is not loſt by Hereſy: their own practice doth evidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them: for theſe that have been ordained in our Churches, are not reordained by them as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial part of Ordination</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152349:34"/>
            <p>And it is certain enough, That a bad Governour, or Governours of the Church may ſend good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into Chriſt's Vineyard: yea Antichriſt himſelf being under the Cloak of Chriſts Vicar, may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute the Offices of Chriſts Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Earthly Court to good men that are willing to ſerve Chriſt. So when Chriſt was upon Earth, the Church was very much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and yet they ſent good Workmen into the Lords Vineyard, ſuch as <hi>Joſeph, Nicodemus,</hi> and othes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude all with thanks to Almighty God, for that he hath been pleaſed to open mine eyes, to ſee the way of truth, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to him to confirm me therein: and my hearty wiſhes, that every one may reject the way of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and be rooted, and built
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152349:35"/>up in Chriſt, and eſtabliſhed in the faith, leſt he be ſpoiled by vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, after the Tradition of Men, after the Rudiments of the World, and not after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come out of</hi> Babylon <hi>my People, leſt ye be partakers of her ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Embrace the true Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is pure in Doctrine, holy in Manners, and faithful to God and the King.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152349:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
